let's start with lecture seven
now memory management
here you have the reading instructions as
always from the
main textbook but also the extra readings
you can have a look if you want from the
Silberschatz
operating
system concepts book
so this lecture together with the following
one about virtual
memory we'll be focusing on basically all
the different
type of memories we have in our computers
I'm talking about main memory caches registers
not really
the disk although it is part of what we will
discuss
we'll discuss how the information is continuously
moved between
slow and fast memories and also how we basically
keep separated
the physical memory from the logical view
from what the processes
and the operating system actually shows to
the processes
and we will see that this distinction between
the logical
and physical memory actually allows for a
lot of beneficial
aspects despite the fact that of course it
has some overheads
some costs
all these things will become more clear during
the lecture
so let's start with the introduction
the goal of the operating system
one of the goals of the operating system we
discussed is
to maximize the CPU utilization
and to do this we run multiple
processes concurrently
in
parallel and all these processes as you can
imagine are sharing
the physical memory of your computer of the
computer you
are using
to run a certain operating system and its
sets of processes
now we have different types of memories in
our computers
and usually there is a tradeoff between their
speed and their
size so you can have extremely large memories
like magnetic
tapes but they are slow in input output operations
or you can have small ones like registers
up here that on
the other end can be extremely fast when it
comes to reading
and writing from them
now we can actually divide these memories
into two groups
the first three here registers caches and
main memory they
can be accessed directly by the CPU
if one core of the CPU wants to read or write
something in
one of these memories it is directly connected
to these
memories so it can just read and write
how much it takes of course depends on the
memory
if it's a register you can be basically performing
a reading
or writing even in one cycle
if it's the main memory it will be several
cycles
the other group is the group of memories that
cannot be directly
accessed by the CPU
physically the CPU needs to go through a
controller
and
then it can reach the other type of memories
like the solid
state disk the hard disk and so on and so
forth
which means of course that it takes way more
time to write
and read from this memory than from the first
three
so in order for the execution to be efficient
what you usually
do is that when you want to run a process
you take what
is written on a disk
the program the set of instructions you want
to run and
you load it into memory
this is why you put the stuff in memory because
in memory
the CPU can directly read and write
and so the interaction to read variables
take the next
instruction and so on and so forth can be
done with a small
number of cycles rather than a lot of cycles
like if we were trying to use the disk as
our let's
say main memory
now as I mentioned in the beginning of the
course in
operating systems you always see this
collaboration
between
the operating system itself and the hardware
and when it comes to managing memory you will
see that
there is a lot of cooperation between the
OS and the hardware
here one of the challenges is if we let the
hardware help
in the management of memory running processes
and so on
but we still want to check
that everything
has been done consistently so we want to ensure
correctness
as I mentioned in the very first lecture here
when introducing
system calls how can we have this correctness
check done
also by the hardware how can actually the
hardware
help the
operating system performing this kind of
checks?
this we will see in the next video